{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A funerary work from this civilization shows two lovers with braided hair, embracing and smiling. The Sarcophagus of the Spouses was created by people in this civilization, as was the Chimera of Arezzo, which was later owned by the Medici family. This civilization, which was wrongly credited with creating the Capitoline Wolf, produced a statue of Apollo found in its city of Veii. For ten points, name this civilization in ancient Italy whose art influenced that of ancient Rome.",
      "answer": "Etruscans"
    },
    {
      "question": "After this man discovered a plan by King Artag to betray him, he invaded Iberia and captured fortresses like Harmozica and Seusamora. This man was selected to replace Lucius Lucullus in a war against Mithridates VI of Pontus. Ptolemy XIII ordered the execution of this man after Julius Caesar defeated him at the Battle of Pharsalus. For ten points, name this Roman general that led the Optimates faction of the Roman Senate against Julius Caesar’s Populares.",
      "answer": [
        "Gnaeus Pompey Magnus",
        "Pompey the Great"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician applied his namesake doctrine after a crisis affecting Camille Chamoun’s Lebanese government. During this man’s Presidency, Francis Gary Powers was shot down while on a reconnaissance mission, sparking the U2 Incident. This man’s foreign policy was spearheaded by his Secretary of State John Foster Dulles, who helped organize the Iranian coup of 1953. For ten points, name this President who previously served as a World War II general.",
      "answer": "Dwight D. Eisenhower"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1944, this man reached “ace in a day” status by, in part, scaring a German pilot into crashing into his wingman. Two nights before his most famous feat, this man broke two ribs riding horses but only told his wife and friend Jack Ridley. This man, who named his plane Glamorous Glennis after his wife, was dropped out of the bomb bay of a B-29 bomber in the experimental Bell X-1 in 1947. For ten points, name this first pilot to break the sound barrier.",
      "answer": "Charles Elwood “Chuck” Yeager"
    },
    {
      "question": "While this leader was traveling in Australia, unknown assailants used a large wood log in an attempt to derail this leader’s train in the Lithgow Plot. Marcus Sargent fired six blank shots at this leader in 1981 during the Trooping the Colour ceremony. In the event of this person’s death, her government will carry out Operation London Bridge. This queen labeled 1992 her “annus horribilis”, in part due to a tell-all book by Princess Diana. For ten points, name this current Queen of England.",
      "answer": "Elizabeth II"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Church of the Holy Sepulchre was destroyed by Fatimid forces after it was reported that miraculous fire jumped onto these things. During the Havdalah ceremony, a braided one of these things is prayed over. Examples of these things with the letters Alpha and Omega are used on Easter in Roman Catholic churches. For ten points, name these objects that, during Chanukah, are held by menorahs and lit from right to left.",
      "answer": "candles"
    },
    {
      "question": "Much of this battle took place at the Chalmette Plantation. Alexander Cochrane helped the losing side in this battle, which led to a siege of Fort St. Phillip. Edward Pakenham led the British in this battle against an army aided by the pirate Jean Lafitte. This battle took place two weeks after the Treaty of Ghent was signed. For ten points, name this victory for Andrew Jackson during the War of 1812, a defense of the most populous city in Louisiana.",
      "answer": "Battle of New Orleans"
    },
    {
      "question": "The 1912 S´aenz Pena Law in Argentina made this action mandatory, a policy that was first implemented in Belgium in 1893. Arrow’s Impossibility Theorem explains a problem with this action when it involves more than two possible options. In 1872, Susan B. Anthony was arrested in Rochester for committing this action, which was addressed by the 19th Amendment. For ten points, name this action through which citizens choose candidates on Election Day.",
      "answer": [
        "voting",
        "word forms",
        "elaborations, like mandatory voting"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An ancient civilization in this modern-day country left the Anitta Text, outlining how the title leader defeated the last king of Zalpuwa. The 1950s Dorak Affair concerned James Mellaart smuggling artifacts from this country after working on the Neolithic city of C¸atalh¨oyu¨k [chat-ul-HOY-ook]. Another discovery in this nation was uncovered by Heinrich Schliemann at Hisarlik six miles from the Dardanelles Strait. For ten points, name this modern-day country where the ancient ruins of Troy are found.",
      "answer": "Turkey"
    },
    {
      "question": "Poor wording in this legislation allowed swindlers to interpret a 12 by 14 requirement to be in inches rather than feet. The 1934 Taylor Grazing Act severely curtailed this legislation. This act was supported by the Timer Culture Act, which gave additional benefits in exchange for planting trees. This act allowed settlers to purchase 160 acres of public land for the cost of a filing fee. For ten points, name this 1862 act that promoted westward expansion.",
      "answer": "Homestead Act"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Timoleon Vassos was born in this country and led an expedition force to assist in an 1897 revolt. That revolt led to this country’s “Black “97” in which the Thirty Days” War was fought over control of an island whose largest city is Heraklion. The Ottoman Empire gained parts of Thessaly from this country in that war, which was fought seven decades after Alexander Ypsilantis led this country’s independence movement. For ten points, name this country that, after leaving the Ottoman Empire, became a kingdom with capital Athens.",
        "answer": "Kingdom of Greece"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Ottoman Empire initially won the Greco-Turkish War of 1897, but eventually was convinced to give Greece control of this island, the site of the Vassos expedition that started the war. Cities on this island include Heraklion and its capital at the time, Chania.",
        "answer": "Crete"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A piece inspired by this war begins with a tone cluster for fifty-two strings and was originally called 8 Minutes, 37 Seconds by Krzysztof Penderecki [krish-toff pen-der-etz-kee]. A cantata about an event during this war begins “I cannot remember everything” and ends with the singing of the Shema. Henryk Gorecki’s Symphony of Sorrowful Songs centers on this war and used text from the wall of a Gestapo prison cell. For ten points, name this war memorialized by “A Survivor From Warsaw.”",
        "answer": "World War II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This composer was inspired by Hitler’s 1941 attack on Russia to write his Leningrad Symphony, which includes a famous “Invasion” theme.",
        "answer": "Dmitri Dmitriyevich Shostakovich"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man had his slave Charlotte Dupuy arrested when she refused to return after being denied a writ of freedom in court. In an attempt to end a secessionist crisis in South Carolina, this politician pushed through the Tariff of 1833. This politician developed the American System, a portion of which, the Maysville Road, was vetoed by Andrew Jackson due to a personal grudge. For ten points, name this Kentucky politician called the “Great Compromiser.”",
        "answer": "Henry Clay"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Henry Clay supported the Tariff of 1833 to end this crisis in which John Calhoun defended his state’s right to classify federal law as unconstitutional.",
        "answer": "Nullification Crisis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A fleet from this country carried out the Raid on the Medway as part of the second of its four wars with England. This country suffered from the first speculative bubble when the price of tulips skyrocketed and then crashed in 1637. William the Silent secured the independence of this country in the Eighty Years” War. In 1672, this country temporarily held off a French invasion by flooding parts of Holland. For ten points, name this country where the Dutch East India Company operated out of Amsterdam.",
        "answer": "The Netherlands"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Dutch East India Company temporarily took control of this Asian island before being removed by Koxinga in 1661.",
        "answer": [
          "Taiwan",
          "Formosa"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this battle, Colonel Jules Gaucher died during the opening attack on outpost Beatrice. The losing side in this battle launched Operation Castor, a massive paratrooper attack. After failing to assist besieged troops at this battle, artillery commander Charles Piroth killed himself with a hand grenade. Christian de Castries, as well as over 10,000 soldiers, were captured in this battle during a massive assault ordered by Vo Nguyen Giap. For ten points, name this 1954 French defeat in Vietnam.",
        "answer": "Battle of Dien Bien Phu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of Dien Bien Phu was launched to cut off a supply line from this country. 10 years later, this country, along with Cambodia, would be controversially bombed by American forces.",
        "answer": "Laos"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At the 1912 Olympics, this man was the U.S. representative in the first modern pentathlon. Joe Angelo saved this man’s life during his command at the Meuse-Argonne Offensive. George C. Scott won, but did not accept, an Oscar for portraying this man, who replaced Lloyd Fredendall after the Battle of Kasserine Pass and infamously slapped two shell-shocked soldiers in Sicily in 1943. For ten points, name this U.S. Army general, nicknamed “Old Blood and Guts,” who led the Third Army during the invasion of France.",
        "answer": "George S. Patton"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The film Patton was co-written by this man, who directed The Godfather and Apocalypse Now.",
        "answer": "Francis Ford Coppola"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "William Wirt developed the Gary Plan to increase efficiency in these institutions. In 1943, the Supreme Court ruled that people at these locations were not required to perform the pledge of allegiance. First amendment rights while at one of these locations were outlined in Tinker v. Des Moines, which stemmed from administrators claiming armbands protesting the Vietnam War were distracting. For ten points, name these locations where students have fought for free speech.",
        "answer": "schools"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The pledge of allegiance case was brought by a member of this denomination. In Chaplinsky v. New Hampshire, which created the fighting words doctrine, a member of this faith was arrested after calling a marshal a fascist.",
        "answer": "Jehovah’s Witness"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A puppet regime in this country was led by an Italian prince who took the name Tomislav II. Alexander I was killed in France by an organization based in this modern-day country, the Nazi-supporting Ustashe. The country secured its independence in the Erdut Agreement after fighting a war against the government of Slobodan Milosevic. For ten points, name this country that, after breaking away from Yugoslavia, established a capital at Zagreb.",
        "answer": "Croatia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Croatian resistance in World War II was led by this revolutionary who became President of Yugoslavia for 27 years starting in 1953.",
        "answer": [
          "Josip Broz Tito",
          "either underlined name"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Banks",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President who declared a bank holiday in the midst of the Great Depression.",
          "answer": "Franklin Delano Roosevelt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Company that, in 2016, was fined millions of dollars for creating thousands of fake accounts.",
          "answer": "Wells Fargo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Financier whose namesake bank merged with Chase Manhattan in 2000.",
          "answer": [
            "John Pierpont “J.P.” Morgan Sr.",
            "JPMorgan Chase"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Central bank of the United States, which sets monetary policy.",
          "answer": "Federal Reserve System"
        },
        {
          "question": "Agency created by the 1933 Banking Act to restore trust in banks by protecting deposits.",
          "answer": [
            "FDIC",
            "Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Banker who was the last leader of the Second Bank of the United States.",
          "answer": "Nicholas Biddle"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who removed that man after winning the Bank War.",
          "answer": "Andrew Jackson"
        },
        {
          "question": "1933 act, sponsored by two senators, that prevented investment banks from taking deposits.",
          "answer": "Glass-Stegall Act"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Popes",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Extremely tiny nation ruled by the Pope recognized in the Lateran Treaty.",
          "answer": "Vatican City"
        },
        {
          "question": "Position within the church, once held by the 1st Duke of Richelieu, whose members elect the new Pope.",
          "answer": "cardinals"
        },
        {
          "question": "Honor guard with a mercenary origin that was established in 1506.",
          "answer": "Pontifical Swiss Guard or Papal Swiss Guard"
        },
        {
          "question": "Warrior pope who fought a war against Venice and founded that honor guard.",
          "answer": "Julius II"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Pope, who was legendarily crucified upside-down.",
          "answer": [
            "Saint Peter",
            "Peter the Apostle",
            "Simon Peter but"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Pope who was shot by a member of the Grey Wolves in 1981.",
          "answer": "John Paul II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who was labeled “Hitler’s Pope.”",
          "answer": "Pius XII"
        },
        {
          "question": "Possibly fictional 9th century figure, the only female Pope.",
          "answer": "Joan"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Global Terrorism",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "British city targeted in the 7/7 bombings.",
          "answer": "London"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital of Somalia where Al Shabaab has carried out dozens of deadly attacks.",
          "answer": "Mogadishu"
        },
        {
          "question": "South American country where FARC launched many attacks before a 2016 ceasefire.",
          "answer": "Colombia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where Ahmed Ben Bella’s FLN used terror against French colonizers.",
          "answer": "Algeria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Town in Scotland that was showered with debris following the explosion of Pan Am Flight 103.",
          "answer": "Lockerbie"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where a discotheque was bombed in 1986 on the orders of Muammar Gaddafi.",
          "answer": "West Berlin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Jerusalem hotel bombed by a Zionist organization in 1946.",
          "answer": "King David Hotel"
        },
        {
          "question": "1978 attack in Iran in which over 400 people burned to death during a showing of The Deer.",
          "answer": "Cinema Rex fire"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man foolishly ignored an offer of 10,000 cataphracts and safe passage from Artavasdes II of Armenia. This businessman created a private (20 pts)",
        "fire brigade of 500 men that would stop working while he negotiated with the tenants over the price of their burning home. After being captured at the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Carrhae by Parthians, this member of the First Triumvirate had molten gold poured down his throat. For ten points, name this general who was possibly the richest man in Roman history."
      ],
      "answer": "Marcus Licinius Crassus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man rejected America’s alliance with France in his open letter “To the Inhabitants of America.” While Military Governor of Philadelphia, this man met with (20 pts)",
        "Peggy Shippen and was later court-martialed for profiting from his position. This man, with the help of Ethan Allen’s Green Mountain Boys, led the capture of (10 pts)",
        "Fort Ticonderoga. John Andr´e was hanged after his plot with this man was discovered. For ten points, name this American general who defected to the British after failing to handover West Point."
      ],
      "answer": "Benedict Arnold"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a novel by this author, Anne Elliot breaks her engagement to the impoverished Frederick Wentworth, only for him to be promoted to Captain for his actions at the Battle of San Domingo and become rich. This author created Colonel Brandon and (20 pts)",
        "Edward Ferrars, who court Elinor and Marianne Dashwood in one work, and wrote about (10 pts)",
        "Fitzwilliam Darcy and Elizabeth Bennet in another novel. For ten points, name this English author of manners novels like Persuasion, Sense and Sensibility, and Pride and Prejudice."
      ],
      "answer": "Jane Austen"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A photograph taken in this state taken at the Travis Air Force Base depicts Lorrie Stirm about to hug her POW father, titled Burst of Joy. Toyo Miyatake documented his incarceration in this state’s (20 pts)",
        "Owens Valley at a location that closed in November 1945; Dorothea Lange also took photos of the (10 pts)",
        "Manzanarinternmentcampinthisstate.Fortenpoints, name this state where Ansel Adams’s photo Moon Over Half Dome was taken at Yosemite National Park."
      ],
      "answer": "California"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this colony, the loss of the exceptionally large Seri cannon led to a prophecy cursing the town of Selangor until its return. The foreign Operation Claret supported this colony’s path to independence, which sparked the (20 pts)",
        "Konfrontasi standoff. This modern-day country was the site of a Chin Peng-led communist (10 pts)",
        "“Emergency” and the location of the majority of the Straits Settlements. For ten points, name this modern-day country that, in 1965, expelled Singapore."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Malaysia",
        "British Malaya"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the prelude to this battle, one side tricked the other into thinking its water purification system had broken. This battle coincided with the attack on (20 pts)",
        "Dutch Harbor. William Halsey was replaced by Raymond Spruance for this battle after being bedridden with shingles. Station (10 pts)",
        "HYPO broke the JN25b code prior to this battle, allowing American forces to follow Yamamoto Isoroku’s fleet. The Akagi, Soryu, and Kaga were sunk during this battle. For ten points, name this decisive 1942 victory over Japan at a namesake atoll."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Midway"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In December 2016, a militant group of this ethnicity called the Freedom Hawks orchestrated a car bombing and suicide bombing in Besiktas, killing dozens of police officers. The 2016 documentary Gulistan, Land of Roses follows a guerilla unit of (20 pts)",
        "women of this ethnicity fighting ISIS. ISIS and this ethnic group were the targets of the Operation Martyr Yalcin airstrikes launched by the (10 pts)",
        "Erdogan [air-doh-wan] regime. The PKK party was founded by members of, for ten points, what ethnic group that aims to create a nation-state in modern-day Syria, Turkey and Iraq?"
      ],
      "answer": "Kurdish people or Kurds"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was replaced by Leo von Caprivi after his ministers were allowed to report to the king. The Kartell, a right-wing parliamentary coalition, led by this man was opposed by the (20 pts)",
        "Centre Party and the Social Democrats. This man supported Adalbert Falk’s May Laws, which targeted the (10 pts)",
        "Catholic Church as part of his “kulturkampf.” In one speech, this man said that the questions of the day would be answered with “iron and blood.” For ten points, name this Chancellor of Prussia who created Germany."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Otto von Bismarck",
        "Otto Eduard Leopold"
      ]
    }
  ]
}